Why does Moscow need Dagestan, I understand,
Зачем Москве Дагестан я понимаю он
Moscow takes people's resources from there,
Москва берёт оттуда там ресурсы
money, and why does Dagestan need Moscow?
людей деньги а зачем Дагестану
Hello Hello, I'm from the city of
Здравствуйте Здравствуйте я из города
Khmelnitsky
Хмельницкий Вы
Where are you from? I'm from Dagestan, Avar, Kumyk,
откуда Я из Дагестана аварец кумык
Dargin,
даргинец
Avar, I understand, somewhere at work,
аварец понял где-то на работе
you're sitting on duty
сидите на дежурстве
today,
сегодня
those security, security, I understand, in short, in
те охрана охрана понял да короче в
Dagestan  all the guards
Дагестане все охранники
Yes, you just need security, you can say we’re on
Да просто надо охраной можно сказать
duty, I understand, look, I’m studying. I’m
дежурим понял смотрите Я вот изучаю Я
from Ukraine myself, but I’m a representative of a
сам из Украины но я вот представитель
research center studying about
исследовательского центра изучаю отно
regional differences in the Russian
региональные отличия в Российской
Federation. Yes, I understand that you have
Федерации Да я так понимаю что у вас
Dagestan, a very ethnically diverse region,
Дагестан очень этнически пёстрый регион
there are a lot of nationalities, a
там очень много национальностей очень
lot of them right
много правильно
so yes yes But the question is what connects you
так да да А вот вопрос что вас связывает
with
с
Moscow, me
Москвой меня
personally, well, why,
лично ну зачем вот зачем Дагестану
why does Dagestan need Moscow? Why does Moscow need Dagestan, I understand
Москва Зачем Москве Дагестан я понимаю
that Moscow takes people’s resources from there,
он Москва берёт оттуда там ресурсы
money, and why does Dagestan
людей деньги а зачем Дагестану
need Moscow? And what remains of Dastana?
Москва А что Дастана остаётся
Well, for example, there
Ну вот например
is. Well, for example, I’m with Azerbaijan  Yes, he
есть Ну я например с вот Азербайджан да
lives there independently,
живёт Независимо там сам себе
manages his own money, develops
распоряжается своими деньгами развивает
his own culture there, faith, and so on Yes,
свою там культуру там веру и так дальше
Dagestan is also a type of oil-bearing region,
Да Дагестан тоже типа нефтеносных регион
like oil is extracted in
у вас типа нефть добывают в
Dagestan, oil and gas Yes, there is access to the Caspian Sea, yes, that
Дагестане нефть газ Да выход в каспию
is, international trade
есть да то есть торговля международная
as well Yes, and it turns out why do you need
также Да Во и получается зачем вам
Moscow, if Moscow takes your
Москва если Москва у вас забирает
resources, money and people, and in
ресурсы деньги и людей а к даёт вам
return
взамен
Moscow gives you something without a
Москва что-то без
clue, I live normally and don’t complain. Yes,
понятия я нормально живу и не жалуюсь Да
I don’t, well, they could live even better and not
я же не ну могли ещё лучше жить и не
complain. Question: Well, why look
жаловаться вопрос Ну Для чего смотрите
when you’re with someone?  something cooperates Yes,
когда кто-то с кем-то сотрудничает Да
this cooperation should be
это сотрудничество должно быть
mutually beneficial yes if Moscow
взаимовыгодное да если Москва у вас
takes something from you yes what you take from
что-то берёт да то что вы берёте у
Moscow what Moscow
Москвы что Москва вам
gives you Well okay Moscow takes it
даёт Ну хорошо Москва берёт нам ничего
doesn’t give us anything What should we do wrong I’m not I’m
не даёт Что нам делать не так Я не я
looking I’m not saying that  you do I
смотрю Я не говорю что вам делать Я
just want to understand how the
просто хочу понять как обустроены
regions in the Russian Federation are organized Yes Toto
регионы в Российской Федерации Да Тото
What Moscow is giving to Dagestan Why
Что даёт Москва Дагестану Для чего
Moscow is giving to Dagestan I don’t know But me too I
Москва не знаю А я вот тоже я Вот мо я
asked in the Trans-Baikal Territory like in
спрашивал в Забайкальском крае типа в
Primorsky In this no one knows what
Приморском В этом никто не знает что
Moscow is giving them well Well  and why these questions What does
Москва ну Ну а к чему эти вопросы Что
Moscow give while I’m studying Yes,
даёт Москва пока я Я изучаю Да я
for example, I note to myself for example
например отмечаю себе например
What ideas did they come up with that Moscow gives Yes, for
Какие идеи придумали что Москва даёт Да
example, a girl from Transbaikal from the
вот например девушка из Забайкальского с
region said that Moscow only gives
края сказала что Москва даёт только
mushrooms Yes, that’s the only thing that Moscow doesn’t
грыбы Да вот Единственное что Москва не
take from the region but gives to  the region is the
забирает из региона а даёт в регион это
coffins of people, it takes money for the war, it
гробы людей забирает на войну деньги
takes taxes, resources, it takes
забирает налоги ресурсы забирает
minerals Yes, it
полезные ископаемые Да назад
processes it all back and brings it in the form of
перерабатывает это всё и приводит в виде
coffins, and where it’s not like that everywhere, it’s not like that, so
гробов а где не так везде же так нет так
look, well, how, why
смотри ну как как Почему ещё раз
look again in Moscow like this, Moscow takes
смотрите в Москве так Москва забирает из
people’s minerals from Dagestan  money from Dagestan Well,
людей ископаемые деньги Дагестана Ну и
from other regions, that’s right Yes from all
из других регионов правильно Да со всех
regions That is, it turns out that Moscow
регионов То есть получается Москва
is parasitizing on these regions, it takes
паразитирует на этих регионах забирает
money, resources and people from there for its own
оттуда деньги ресурсы и людей для своих
ambitions for entertainment. And back,
каких-то амбиций для развлечений А назад
what does it give besides coffins? It’s back that
Что даёт кроме гробов Вот назад приходят
only coffins come to the regions. These are the people.
в регионы только гробы Вот это люди
could they have said back why our Dastan
могли сказать назад почему у нас Дастан
is developing like this is developing
развивается так развивается из-за того
because the Dagestanis are being taken away from you.
что дагестанцам Ну у вас забирают
For example, they took 10 billion from you there. Yes, they took 10 billion from you to the
Например у вас забрали там 10 млрд Да в
federal budget and returned a
бюджет федеральный а вернули вам
billion to you. How is it a subsidy, a
миллиард Как там субвенция
handout, that is, 9 billion was taken from you? Well,
подачка то есть 9 млрд у вас забрали Ну
at the expense of what  look at the expense of what
за счёт чего смотрите за счёт чего
Moscow is building Moscow City, these are all
Москва строит Москва Сити вот эти Всё
shorter show-off metro due to what resource
короче понты метро за счёт чего ресурс
They are extracting oil gas that Moscow
Они что добывают нефть газ что Москва
is extracting
добывает
nothing And what difference does it make who produces
ничего А какая разница кто добывает
Moscow is the
Москва - это
center So why can’t it Why
центр Так почему не может Почему центром
can’t the center be Makhachkala or Derbent
не может быть Махачкала или Дербент
for example, well  because Makhachkala is not
например ну потому что Махачкала не
Moscow and why is it not Moscow,
Москва так А почему она не Москва
look when Azerbaijan was in the
вот смотрите когда Азербайджан был в
Soviet Union everything went to the center in Moscow
Советском Союзе всё шло в центр в Москву
Azerbaijan became independent everything goes to the
Азербайджан стал независимым всё идёт в
center in Baku and everything is distributed throughout
центр в Баку и всё и и распределяется по
Azerbaijan in the interests of
азербайджану в интересах
the Azerbaijanis we need to become independent I
азербайджанцев надо стать независимым Я
don’t know  Well, well, it’s not for me to decide what
не знаю что ну это ж не мне решать что
you need. If, for example, you want to live so well.
вам надо Если вам например Так хорошо
Well, I won’t force someone
жить Ну я же не буду заставлять кого-то
to live. I’m just
жить Я просто так
better this way. Together with Moscow, I think so. And with
лучше Вот вместе с Москвой Я думаю так А
what, and if you
чем чем а если
separate, and if you separate, what will be better
отдели а если отделиться что лучше будет
? Well  for example, Azerbaijan separated and
Ну например Азербайджан отделился что
lives poorly Let’s say we separated, we
плохо живёт Допустим отделились мы у нас
succeeded, let’s say who will leave us
получилось допустим да кто нас оставит
later in the sense of
потом в смысле
leaving Well, this is a tidbit, what a
оставит Ну это же лакомый кусок какой
tidbit of what a North Caucasus Well,
лакомый кусок кака Северный Кавказ Ну
look, Well, who has now taken,
вот смотрите Ну вот а кто сейчас забрал
for example,
например
Azerbaijan Why Azerbaijan can
Азербайджан Почему Азербайджан может
live and develop and  Dagestan won’t be
жить и развиваться а Дагестан там не
able to do it there, for example,
сможет например
they won’t give it. Why won’t they give it
даста не дадут Почему не
on this side?
дадут с этой стороны Турция не даст с
Turkey won’t give it. On the other hand, they won’t give it. No why. Well, look, let’s say that in terms of culture and spirit, Turkey is closer to you than
духу Турция ближе чем
Russia Turkey
Россия Турция
Yes, Muslims Well, like Muslims Look,
Да мусульмане Ну как мусульмане Смотри
everyone there is Muslims No, well  anyway, it’s a
все там мусульмане Не ну всё равно это
Muslim country anyway Yes,
мусульманская всё равно страна Да она
although it’s secular, it has a Muslim
хоть и светская так но с мусульманским
component, yes Russia is unclear
компонентом да Россия - это непонятно
what kind of country it is, it positions itself as
какая там она позиционирует себя как
Orthodox, but you’ll understand what type of
православная но хер поймёшь Какая типа
security service country Yes, why Azerbaijan
чекистская страна Да почему Азербайджан
lives here, Kazakhstan lives yes That is, you
живёт вот Казахстан живёт да То есть вы
get when you got there  to the Russian
получается когда попали в Российскую
Empire only about 150 years ago,
империю только где-то 150 лет назад
just you and Russia were a short period of
всего вы с Россией маленький промежуток
time. We lived in Ukraine and then
вре Мы в Украине жили и то дольше нас
Russia captured us longer than us, but you in dem and
Россия захватила столе вот а вас в дем и
we freed ourselves and live in peace, we
мы ничего освободились и живём спокойно
develop like ourselves, yes, that is, if for
развиваемся типа сами да то есть если
example, if  Moscow will decide that it
например вот если Москва решит что типа
doesn’t need the Caucasus, yes, that’s it. She’s tired,
не нужен ей Кавказ да Всё да Устала она
you won’t protest that No,
Вы же не будете протестовать что Нет
take us, take everything, but please, in
берите берите нас всё но пожалуйста в
Russia, Moscow won’t get tired of the Caucasus. And
России Москва не устанет Кавказа А
why do we have personally important objects here,
почему чески важные объекты тут у нас
as well as it must be held because
как а его надо удерживать потому что у
Moscow, look  Where is
Москвы смотри Где в том
this whole Russian Federation? Yes,
что вся вот эта Российская Федерация Да
as a prototype of the Russian Empire, it
как прототип Российской империи она
was supported by the army of the
держалась на армии
PSB police. Yes, this is on the power
ПСБ полиции Да вот это на силовом
apparatus, most of it has now died in
аппарате большинство его сейчас сдохло в
Ukraine, yes. That is, in fact, in Russia, let’s
Украине да То есть фактически у России
say there is no such thing. Yes. All that will remain is,
такого скажем нету да Останется только
for example, some kind of click  or there will
например какой-то щелчок либо какой-то
be some kind of military coup like
будет военный переворот типа как
Prigozhin marched on Moscow there, or Putin
Пригожин там на Москву шёл либо Путин
will die there, or what, and there will be a parade of
умрёт там или что да и будет парад
sovereignty, for example Tatarstan, in
суверенитетом например Татарстан вот в
Tatarstan they are very strong, too. In the
Татарстане очень сильные тоже они же В
ninety-second year, they also held
девяносто втором году тоже проводили
a referendum on sovereignty, so if the
референдум о суверенитете вот если
Islamic regions of Tatarstan are Bashkartastan  that’s how they
исламские регионы Татарстан башкартастан
declare independence. Well,
так само объявляют о независимости Ну
that doesn’t mean that you just came out alone
этоже не значит что вы просто одни вышли
and that’s it. And who is stopping you from uniting
и всё А кто вам мешает объединяться
later into some kind of Confederation or
потом в какие-то себе Конфедерации или
union like the European Union? Yes, there is
союзы вот на Европейский союз Да есть
Poland, there is France, absolutely
Польша есть есть Франция абсолютно
independent countries, everyone does
независимые страны каждый себе делает
what they want, but  they agreed on
что хочет во но они договорились об
open
открытых границах
trade borders, it’s just that many people know what
торговли просто многим знаете тут в чём
the problem is here, that many are afraid to think even
проблема что многие боятся думать даже
because they had no experience. Yes, it’s like we
потому что не было опыта Да вот мы как
lived in the Soviet Union. Yes, now we
бы жили в Советском Союзе Да сейчас Мы
Ukrainians have lived separately, we understand how
украинцы пожили отдельно мы понимаем как
it is, yes we can develop our country,
это да мы можем развивать свою страну
our people  because we want Yes and not to
свой народ так как мы хотим Да и не
give it away Previously, we had all the products there,
отдавать Раньше у нас там все продукты
everything was taken to Moscow and Moscow by Zhirov
всё забирало в Москву да Москва Жирова
during the Union And all the
при Союзе А все
Republics suffered Yes now Well,
Республики мучились Да теперь Ну
friend, we can develop the way
подругому мы можем развиваться так как
we want and that’s it Well,
мы хотим да и всё так
yes, we have a clan in Dagestan  the
что Ну да у нас в Дагестане клановая
system basically happens if Moscow
система в основном бывает если Москва от
separates from Moscow then the order in general
Москвы отделиться ту порядка вообще уже
can already be said not to wait, well, it won’t
можно сказать не ждать не ну как не
be Well, well, Azerbaijan shared
будет Ну хорошо вот Азербайджана делился
that there is no order there
что нет порядка
will be no order So why won’t there be and
не будет порядка Так почему не будет а
now Well, now that there is order
сейчас Ну а сейчас что порядок есть У
We have normal order yes  And what is the
нас нормально порядок да А в чём в чём
order and what will not happen? What will not happen, what will happen
порядок и чего не будет Вот что не будет
if the department from Russia What will
что случатся если отде от России Что
happen to the
случится с
order, they will start stealing, there
порядком воровать начнут коррупция
will be corruption, and so on Well, yes, so
будет коррупция будет она и так са Ну
look, now
так вот да так что смотри вот сейчас
there is corruption. Yes, what will change?
есть коррупция Да что изменится Например
Russia won’t be with you
если не будет России с вами
The devil
Чёрт его
knows, you just know, there’s a
знает просто ещё знаешь вот Есть такая
topic I’m just studying in Russia, they did
тема я просто изучаем в России сделали
something like this, uh, what’s
такое что вот Ээ как это называется у
your name for a subsidized region, here I’m
вас дотационный регион вот вам
telling you that Dagestan is a subsidized
Рассказываю что Дагестан дотационный
region,
регион
well, yes, for some reason, Bashkartastan is a
так Ну да так вот башкартастан почему-то
subsidized region  that is, regions in
дотационный регион то есть регионы в
which there is oil and gas. Yes, for example, there
которых есть нефть и газ Да например там
you have gas, by the way, or only oil, in
у вас газ есть кстати или только нефть в
Dagestan
Дагестане
there is gas, or only
есть газ или только
oil, we
нефть у нас
also have gas, and for example, a region in
газ тоже есть да как например регион в
which oil and gas is produced may be
котором добывает нефть и газ может быть
subsidized, that is, this is how they deceive  in the
дотационный то есть вот как обманывают в
World Cup What are
ЧМ В чём
your subsidies and taxes? So we will
дотационные ваших да налого Значит мы
give you a subsidy, they took you there conditionally, there are
дам вам дотацию вас забрали там условно
10 trillion. Yes, they give 1
там 10 триллион Да отдают 1
trillion, but here they don’t absorb 1 trillion;
триллион вот у нас и то 1 триллион не
they don’t have time. Well, how come they don’t
успевают Ну как это они не
have time? I don’t know what you hear every
успевают не знаю ка что слышишь каждый
year there  they managed to appropriate it, they
год там не успели это присвоить обратно
send something back, and you know why?
отправляют что-то А знаешь почему Потому
Because look, because that’s what Moscow does.
что смотри потому что Москва как делает
Yes, it gives out money and so on. So we
Да она выдаёт деньги да и го Так мы
give out so much nominally. Yes, you
номинально выдаём столько Да освоить Вы
can master only part of them; you will
можете только часть из них остальную
return the rest and say that you can’t make it in time and
вернёте и скажете что не успеть и
therefore you can’t have time.  So you believe that there is
поэтому не успевает Вот вы верите что
not enough time to master so much
столько не успевает
Well, right then, Moscow doesn’t
освоить Ну прямо вот и Москва тогда не
appoint a manager who can
ставит менеджера который сможет
master it like this, yes.
освоить вот так вот
So, that’s
да Так
good. Maybe you have some interesting questions. Yes, I do
хорошо Может у вас какие-то вопросы есть
n’t understand anything interesting about politics at all. Okay, let’s
ничего не интересного понял Хорошо давай
all the
всего
best and
хорошего да
those  who is listening to us from the Russian
те кто нас слушает из Российской
Federation Yes, these peoples have
Федерации Да у вот этих народов есть
a fear that we will not survive ourselves,
боязнь как мы не выживем сами нас
someone else will take us over, Yes, the ladies will come for a
захватят кто-то другие Да придут на
tasty morsel,
лакомый кусочек
we are economically poor, that is, Russia
дамы экономически мы бедные то есть вот
makes them such fears that as if
им Россия делает такие страхи что как бы
without Russia they are all In short,  what will happen I
без России всё они Короче а что будет Я
ask what is the order that there
спрашиваю что какой порядок что
will be corruption now there is corruption
коррупция будет сейчас коррупция есть
and so
уних И так
on
дальше